<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Observations on the last Dutch wars, in the years 1672 and 1673. with some reflections upon the city and country.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B04600</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O104</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219204</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">53299205</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 53299205</idno>
            <idno type="VID">179945</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B04600)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179945)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2808:50)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Observations on the last Dutch wars, in the years 1672 and 1673. with some reflections upon the city and country.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through with slight loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dutch War, 1672-1678 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:179945:1"/>
            <p>OBSERVATIONS ON THE LAST Dutch Wars, In the Years 1672, and 1673.</p>
            <p>WITH SOME REFLECTIONS UPON THE CITY and COUNTRY.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Deut. 23. 9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>When the Hoſt goeth forth againſt thine Enemies, then keep thee from every wicked thing.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:179945:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:179945:2"/>
            <head>OBSERVATIONS ON THE LAST Dutch Wars, etc.</head>
            <p>I It being my fortune, as well as other younger Brothers, to run the risk of the world, to live gentily; it was my chance to be in the laſt Dutch Wars, where through my own obſervation and the Sailers complaint, I took notice of theſe three things: Firſt, the general neglect of the Lords Day throughout the whole Fleet, we working upon the Sunday as much, if not more, than we do upon others, and that whilſt we are in harbour; and all this is done under the Name of Expedition: And when we are at Sea, a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander thinks himſelf ſufficiently excuſed to God and the World, if he can find any trifling buſineſs to ſhift off his Chaplain from the duty of the day; if it be but the providing of a Dinner for two or three of his Brother Captains; and a Lieutenants Command for a Rope for the Boat, ſhall be ſooner anſwered with Boatſwain's call, than the Bell for prayers: And this is exactly contrary to the firſt Article of War, <hi>Anno decimo tertio Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roli Secundi Regis:</hi> That all Commanders, Captains, and Officers at Sea, ſhall cauſe the publick Worſhip of Almighty God, according to the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> Eſtabliſhed by Law, to be ſolemnly, orderly, and reverently performed in the reſpective Ships; and that Prayers and Preachings by the reſpective Chaplains in holy orders of the reſpective Ships, be performed diligently; and that the Lords day be obſerved according to Law. He that was ever able to read his Bible, can tell that <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s Sword prevailed no longer than <hi>Moſes</hi> held up his hands, and had it not been for <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Prayers, <hi>Joſhua,</hi> for all his valour, had been defeated. But we like the Scribes, Phariſees, and Hypocrites, pay Tithes of Mint, Anniſe, and Cummin, but omit the weightier matters of the Law; and think that Powder and Bullet will do ſufficient Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without the bleſſing of God; and that a Commander ſaying Bear in,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:179945:3"/>and keep your Luff, ſhall as ſoon put a Fleet to flight, as <hi>Gideon</hi> diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit an Hoſt; but let us remember that it was the Sword of the Lord and <hi>Gideon:</hi> And we ſee that God in <hi>Deut.</hi> 20. aſſigneth an employment to the Prieſts, as well as to the Officers of the Camp: But they cry out what good do theſe Churchmen do? And as they are little regarded there, ſo are they not taken notice of when they come home; as if there were no reſpect or preferment deſerved by venturing their Lives in the ſervice of God and their King. This fault is not only to be found in his Majeſty's Navy, but alſo to be deplored in the Country, the Lords Day being ſet apart only for ſome idle buſineſs, which we cannot afford our ſelves time enough to do in the Week; or otherwiſe to run to hear a man that preach's twice a day, calls us Saints and the Children of God, but never inſtructs us what we muſt do for the attaining of theſe Titles, and this only amounts to ſpiritual pride; for they being once puffed up with being the Children of God, they never think of honouring their Fathers and Mothers according to that Law which God hath enacted. Such that pride themſelves in the knack of Preaching, and neglect Catechiſing; make more Rebels than good Subjects: Two ſuch Parſons I hear of not far off, who ſtrive to out-Preach one another; not, I gueſs, who ſhould make the beſt Chriſtians, and conſequently the beſt Subjects; but who ſhall get the moſt popular Applauſe, the Country People being more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted with a well noſed Tone, than Senſe and Reaſon. This might ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be remedied, were thoſe Acts put in execution, which are made for the obſerving of the Lords Day: But alas! moſt of our Juſtices underſtand nothing but to cry ſo ho to a brace of Greyhounds, and to ſpeak well to a pack of Dogs; and as much Law as to take away a man's Gun, to make him pay his Fine for killing of a Hare or a Pheaſant, and threaten to whip a Beggar to ſave an Alms; but in the more weighty points of the Law, would be baffled upon the Bench by every High-ſhooe; were it not for thoſe worthy Gentlemen, who never made profeſſion of the Law, but have made it their ſtudy, and thoſe that have been bred to that noble Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and are in that honourable Commiſſion: Such Peruk'd Novices rendring the name of a Juſtice as ridiculous, as a Fool doth that of a Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy-man. This day was very exactly obſerved by the French, and very much to our ſhame; and how unreaſonable is it ſince God hath given us ſix for own labour, we don't, according to his command, allow him the ſeventh for his ſervice?</p>
            <p>The ſecond is that dreadful Prophanation of the Lords Name, for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sailer can ring a peal of Oaths as true as any of your <hi>London</hi> Huffs, to whom if your back be towards, when you hear him open, you can't diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:179945:3"/>him by his mouth from one of your Town Gallants, for he carries the ſhauntee behaviour in his Tongue, though not in his Hat and Knee: And this is exactly contrary to the ſecond Article of War, <hi>Anno Decimo Tertio Caroli Secundi Regis:</hi> Every Perſon and Perſons in his Majeſties pay, uſing unlawful and raſh Oaths, Curſings, Execrations, Drunkenneſs, Uncleanneſs, or other ſcandalous Actions in derogation of Gods honour, and corruption of good manners, ſhall be puniſhed by Fine, Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or otherwiſe, as the Court Marſhal ſhall think fit. This, as I have been told, was puniſhed by the gallant Earl of <hi>Sandwich,</hi> with the loſs of their victuals for that day; and they themſelves, I have heard, in a Godly humour complain and ſay, For theſe two things we do not proſper; and that it was not ſo in <hi>Oliver</hi>'s days: And we know that God will not hold him guiltleſs that taketh his Name in vain. Yet though they look upon this and other Sins as Beams in their Brothers, they only eſteem them as Motes in their own eyes; and moſt of them, like our em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pty Bullies, think not the other words (which God knows in reſpect of Oaths and Curſes to be very few) to have any thing of Luſtre without theſe foyls; and many of them like ſome of our Gentlemen, are made up of nothing but Oaths and Execrations: ſo that if men were but aboard a Ship, they need not ſend for ſuch a one to hear him ſwear, for there they may have their ears deafned with this helliſh Thunder, which will give as ſmart and as brisk claps from their Jaws, as from the mouths of thoſe formal Fops, who made it their ſtudy to let them off with a Grace. And if the Fine for it were appropriated to his Majeſty's uſe, it would (until this vice was reform'd) amount to much more than Chimney-money: Yet however if puniſhed according to Law, our Corporations would quickly be provided of ſufficient Stocks to employ their Poor in work; and if every Seaman did pay his Twelvepence, his Majeſty might without any charge to himſelf and Subjects, relieve all the Slaves in <hi>Turky.</hi> But this and the forementioned Law (with many others were moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently well enacted, but never throughly executed.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I never ſaw any real love betwixt the Commanders, they being diſtinguiſhed by two Names, the Terpolian and the Gentile; the Terpolian envying the Gentile, and yet neither the <hi>Gentile</hi> or the <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polian</hi> heartily loving one another: For let them careſs one another never ſo kindly, yet as ſoon as they are parted, they will jeer and ſcoff at him, whom they have but a little before took about the Neck and kiſſed; a pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Complement which becomes the Sons of <hi>Cupid</hi> and the Daughters of <hi>Venus,</hi> and not the Sons of <hi>Mars.</hi> This makes me believe that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard their own private, before the publick Intereſt, and don't ſo diligently
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:179945:4"/>obſerve the Fighting Inſtructions, of which Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> was ſo jealous, that in one Fight he commanded that one ſhould ſtand upon the head, and another upon the Poop of every Ship, to obſerve the performance of him who was next a Head and next a Stern to him: And, as I have been told, Sir <hi>Edward Spragg</hi> had always his Proſpective Glaſs at his Eye, to behold the behaviour of thoſe that were in his Squadron. If there are any private grudges amongſt them, methinks they might lay them aſide, till they have ended the publick quarrel; and not imitate thoſe, whom <hi>Hudibras</hi> in the ſecond <hi>Canto</hi> of his third Part, ſo ingeniouſly deſcribes.
<q>
                  <l>Lay publick Bills aſide for private,</l>
                  <l>And make 'em one another drive out;</l>
                  <l>Divert the Great and Neceſſary</l>
                  <l>With Trifles to Conteſt and Vary.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>I only mention this, for if I were Seaman enough to give any inſtances, I ſhould not, for the reaſon which the Learned <hi>Hooker</hi> gives in his Book of Eccleſiaſtical Polity, <hi>pag.</hi> 1. He that goeth about to perſwade a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, that they are not ſo well governed as they ought to be, ſhall never want attentive and favourable hearers, becauſe they know the manifold defects whereunto every kind of Regiment is ſubject; but the ſecret letts and difficulties, which in publick proceedings are innumerable and inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, they have not ordinarily the judgment to conſider; and becauſe ſuch as openly reprove ſuppoſed diſorders of State, are taken for princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Friends to the common benefit of all, and for men that carry ſingular freedom of mind; under this fair and plauſible colour, whatſoever they utter paſſeth for good and currant. That which wanteth in the weight of their Speech, is ſupplied by the aptneſs of mens minds to accept and believe it. So that if my Pen were able to reveal the leaſt miſhap in his Majeſty's affairs, I ſhould preſently have the Tongues of our Coffee-Politicians come into our aſſiſtance, and make it a grand fault and a downright miſcarriage. They, who whilſt they are ſmoaking their Pipes of Tobacco, can Rigg, Victual, and Man a Fleet, ſet to Sea, Fight the Dutch upon the Galloper and never run aground, beat them at <hi>Southwold Bay;</hi> and before they have whiffed out their Pipes, can return again with victory, without the loſs of either Legs or Arms; yet after all the Fire and Smoak they have been in, dare not board their Coffee-diſhes without much huffing and puffing, for fear of ſcalding their Chops: Theſe Turky News mongers, who with their Pipes and Diſhes look as learnedly, as the Mahometan in the Sign doth with theſe Ornaments, often tell for truth their own inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:179945:4"/>Thus they reported that the Duke of <hi>York</hi> was aſhore at <hi>South-wold</hi> a Feaſting, and the reſt of the Captains a drinking, which was a damnable lye; for he was never aſhore from the nineteenth of <hi>April,</hi> until the eighteenth of <hi>September;</hi> and, as my Captain told me, had given ſtrict Command that no Sea Captain ſhould go from his Ship; And I never heard that any were miſſing from their Ships in the time of Fight, unleſs it were ſome Land Officers and ſome Sea Lieutenants, who were ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhore, to ſee their men fill their water, and to haſten them aboard again when they had done. And although this Engagement was fought over again at the Coffee Table, and the Dutch routed by thoſe who only carry in their Noddles the models of Fights, and the valour of Soldiers in their Fancies; yet let me tell them, that it was fought with excellent valour and conduct by his Highneſs the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> who had the <hi>Prince</hi> and the Saint <hi>Michael</hi> diſabled under him, and hoiſted his Standard aboard the Royal <hi>London.</hi> The Royal <hi>Katherine</hi> was taken, and after ſhe had been in the Enemies poſſeſſion three hours, was retaken by her own Ships com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany: The <hi>Henry</hi> (after the loſs of her Captain, the valiant <hi>Digby,</hi> who although he had loſt his hand, did loſe none of his heart; for it is no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er dreſt but he is again upon Deck to encourage his men, and falls by a ſmall Shot) having loſt moſt of her other Officers, and being diſabled in her Maſts and Rigging, fell into the hand of the Enemy; but is retaken by that modeſt and gallant Gentleman Captain <hi>Roger Strickland</hi> in the <hi>Ply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> who for this ſervice was deſervedly Knighted; beſides the taking of one man of War of theirs, with the ſinking of divers others: And had not the next day proved thick and hazy, few Dutch Ships had went home to have told the News; for we having the wind of them, the Duke was reſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have fought them Yard Arm and Yard Arm. The bloody Flag was put out twice, but it is no ſooner out, but there came ſuch thick miſts, that we could not ſee the Dutch Fleet, notwithſtanding we were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt within ſhot of it: But oh! we loſt the Royal <hi>James:</hi> It is true we did, but I ſhall not now ſtay to anſwer you by demanding your Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to ſome Queſtions, but expect to hear, ſince there is ſuch need of your wit, valour, and conduct, that you have laid aſide your womens weapons (I mean your impertinent and reviling Tongues) that you have broke your Pipes and Coffee diſhes, and that all your ſcattered Forces are drawn up into a main body, and that you are marching into <hi>Scotland</hi> under the Command of one of your Great, but inſignificant Fops; and when we ſhall hear that you are advanced within a mile of the Rebels Camp, and are intrenched upon the top of ſome high hill within ſight of them, we ſhall expect a Pacquet that your breath did prove more deſtructive than a Plague,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:179945:5"/>and that your eyes, like the Baſilisk's, did kill the Camp at a diſtance; for your valour conſiſts only of a little prate, and your Politicks of a preme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditated diſcourſe: For had your Actions been as great as your Talk, without doubt the French King had employed many Regiments of Coffee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teers in his ſervice; but that he knew the Gentlemen at Arms would do more execution than you with your bluſtring blabs. From you Jacks of all Trades it is returned to our publick ſpirited Country Gentlemen, who drink for and ſtand to their Country, and courſe and hunt, who ſwallow your News with as much eagerneſs as they do a Bumper to a Miſs, and give you giddy Politicians as much veneration, as a wiſe man doth an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle of State; immediately ſetting to work to get your Letters <hi>memoriter,</hi> that they may be able to repeat them with as much wit as gravity, the next time they meet their Tenants over a Tub of Ale about ſome Town buſineſs, where they are ſure to be admired and to have their Tenants Hats off with their Pots in their Hands, and all of them ready at the period to drink their Landlords good health, wiſhing all their Governors like their Worſhips; with which applauſe they are ſo much tickled, that to admire their wiſdom they turn their Opticks in upon it, and after they have took a ſevere view of their long reach, they think no Pilots ſo fit to bring the Ship of State into harbour as themſelves; when alas! moſt of them are not able to manage their own Perſons, much leſs work their own little Yachts as they ſhould do. The wooden Shooe need not have been thrown into the Speaker's Chair, to have hindred his Majeſty's proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; for let our Country Gentlemen look home, and they will find in their own Lordſhips many poor Tenants, that have waſted their ſtocks upon their Grounds, and are forced to go barefoot and barelegg'd, being kept at the charge of their other Tenants, who though they may eat Leeks and Onions, yet ſeldom meat to the full; eſpecially amongſt thoſe Landlords whoſe Country has given them good Eſtates, but <hi>France</hi> their grand breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Yet theſe poor men muſt and will open with their Landlords, and run full cry againſt great Taxes, though they be never ſo much for the good and benefit of the whole Nation, never conſidering at our <hi>Lady</hi> and <hi>Michaelmas</hi> days, how deaf they are to their juſt deſires for ſome abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their wonted Rents, or the giving them a ſmall ſtick for their help of repairs; being never willing to eaſe them but out of the ſtock of State. As they employ their ſmall Rhetorick to diminiſh Taxes, ſo on the other ſide they do it to raiſe their Rents; and if any Perſon ſtand up for his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Property (the things ſo much ſought after) he ſhall preſently be diſcharged, and muſt march off at our <hi>Lady day,</hi> unleſs by foregoing his right, he makes a Compoſition with his Landlord. Nay, if a Freeholder
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:179945:5"/>doth ſtand up for his Property againſt the great man of the Town, he ſhall be threatned with ruine, and not him alone but a whole Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration if they diſpleaſe him: And how ſhall this be brought to paſs? why, by giving themſelves and their Servants that great ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denyal of not taking their wonted ſwills of its only Manufacture cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Ale. Thus moſt Country Gentlemen in their Stations imitate the French, and if their Tenants Daughters are handſom, always execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Law of <hi>Ewen</hi> the Scotch King, and only revile our merciful Soveraign, becauſe they cannot be <hi>Nero</hi>'s to the whole Nation. But this is not all, for after every Fight you ſhall have your Country Villages filled with a parcel of idle Fellows, who pretend to be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Seamen or Soldiers, complaining that they are forced to run away for want of Victuals, how they are cheated of their Pay, and of the ill Conduct of their Commanders; crying out their Country is betrayed: Such Raſcals Reports being as Authentick with the Vulgar, as an Account from the Admiral is to his Majeſty after a Council of War, for the particulars of the Engagement; and are as much crowded for their News, as a Ballad Singer in the Market is for his Ditty. Theſe incorrigible Rogues, if taken up and ſent to his Majeſty's Plantations, would not only eaſe, but alſo might prove very ſerviceable to their King and Country howſoever, if taken and ſent to the Houſe of Correction according to Law. And thus far I ſhall vindicate his Majeſty's Affairs by experience, that no man wanted his Victuals aboard, unleſs it were for a fault, and if they were put to ſhort Allowance (which is very ſufficient to maintain any reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able man) they had their pinch-gut mony paid them as ſoon as they came into harbor, and no man went without his pay, unleſs he was made run by the Clerk of the Cheeque. But at parting, let me repeat to you Sir <hi>Robert Cotton</hi>'s Preface to his twenty four Arguments con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Popiſh Practices: I am not ignorant (ſaith he) that this latter Age hath brought forth a ſwarm of buſie heads, which mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the great myſteries of State by the rule of their ſelf conceited wiſdoms, but if they would conſider that the Common-Wealth, (though I think the Kingdom the better name) Governed by grave Counſellors, is like unto a Ship directed by a skilful Pilot, to whom the neceſſities of Occaſions and grounds of Reaſon, why he ſteereth to this or that part of the Compaſs are better known than to thoſe that ſtand aloof off, they would perhaps be more ſparing, if not more wary in their Reſolutions. Indeed I confeſs, that our mouths ought always to be open againſt Popery, but I would not have their Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meters
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:179945:6"/>exceed the Ring of Charity; for had not good Language and good Carriage been a point of Religion as well as of Civility, the Apoſtle had not commanded his <hi>Corinthians</hi> (<hi>Ep.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 32.) to give no Offence, neither to the Jews, nor to the Gentiles, nor to the Church of God. But ſince we have the Ship of <hi>Rome</hi> to the Leeward of us, and are pouring in all our Broadſides upon her, ſo that ſhe muſt needs ſink, unleſs ſhe prove more impenetrable than ſhe hath done infallible; let us keep our Stern chace out againſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Enemy, who now claps on all the Sail he can, and intends to get up with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and in this Engagement wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther her, and once more make her ſtrike ſail to him: I mean <hi>Jack Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> whoſe hot headed Zeal hath been more Injurious to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> than the Romiſh Flames; for they only lighted an Army of her Martyrs to heaven, but this hath raiſed an Hoſt of Phanaticks perpetually to torment her; and though they pretend to be men of tender Conſciences, yet when they had took her, they proved more hard hearted than the moſt inveterate Romaniſts, and outed more men of their Livings in the ſpace of three years, (ſays Doctor <hi>Heylin</hi> in his Hiſtory of them, <hi>lib.</hi> 13. <hi>pag.</hi> 459. <hi>paragr.</hi> 30.) than were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived by the Papiſts in the Reign of Queen <hi>Mary:</hi> And for their inhumane cruelties they did not come far behind them, as you may ſee in Doctor <hi>Heylin</hi>'s Bill of Mortality of the Clergy of <hi>London, lib.</hi> 13. <hi>pag.</hi> 455. <hi>paragr.</hi> 29. For they did not only Impriſon, Plunder, and put to Flight; but expoſed, in Ships, their Perſons to the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of a Raging Sea, their Wives and Children they turned out of doors to gnawing Hunger and pinching Poverty; whilſt theſe Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, with long Prayers and Vultures Stomachs, devour their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates: And when with their ſeditious whinings, they had model'd our beauteous Church according to their Schiſmatical Humour, ſhe appeared a greater Monſter than <hi>Apelles</hi>'s Maſterpiece. But moderate and temperate men who were good Subjects, and afterwards ſome of them Martyrs, drew this; the other being the product only of hot-brain'd Jack's tumultuous and ſeditious Fancy. Our Church hath ſo often routed the Pope's Legions, that his Combatants have thrown away their Argumentative Arms, and have took up Sword, Fire, and Piſtol, to reduce us into the ſubjection, not only of the Biſhop, but Monarch of <hi>Rome:</hi> So when the Presbyterians can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not out-do us by dint of Argument, they imitate the furious Goddeſs in the Poet.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:179945:6"/>
               <q>Flectere ſi nequeo ſuperas, Acheronta movebo.</q>
            </p>
            <p>If Heaven won't defend their unjuſt cauſe, they are ſure Hell will, and preſently they bring in the Devil for their Diſputant; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall not venture to frame a Glaſs that may deſcribe theſe Conjurers, leſt, with the famous <hi>Sherlock,</hi> I ſhould have a Dialogue with <hi>Satan.</hi> Their Glaſſes now are all ſet about the Room, let them look into <hi>Fabian Philips</hi> his <hi>Veritas inconcuſſa,</hi> and there they may behold themſelves, ſetting the beſt of Kings for a mark to my Lord of <hi>Eſſex</hi>'s Canon: Let them look into the Hiſtory of Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency, and there they may ſee themſelves not only the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Rogues, but alſo the meereſt Fools in Nature: Let them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold themſelves in Biſhop <hi>Bramhal,</hi> and if a Presbyterian and a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt can there diſtinguiſh Countenances, I don't know my own face from anothers. Let them look upon themſelves in <hi>Heylin</hi>'s Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of them, and there they will appear to be the only Incendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aries of the World; And if ever they would be accounted Loyal Subjects, they muſt clap on a thicker Mask than that which Mr. <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> took off; for King-killing is a Principle of the Presbyterians as well as of the Jeſuit, which they deſperately maintained and throughly executed: For when King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt had parted with thoſe Regal Jewels to them, that if they had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered him to have lived, he would only have been <hi>Magni Nominis umbra,</hi> nothing would quench their fiery Zeal, and ſatisfie their unſatiable deſires, but his innocent blood; they being reſolved to murther him by the Sword of the Law, or the Law of the Sword. Wherefore Mr. <hi>Chriſtopher Love</hi> declares their minds, in his Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at <hi>Uxbridge</hi> Treaty, <hi>pag.</hi> 32. 'Twas the Lord (ſaith he) that troubled <hi>Achan,</hi> becauſe that he troubled <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Oh that in this our State-Phyſicians (he meant Cut-Throats ſure) would reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble God, to cut off thoſe from the Land who have diſtemper'd it: <hi>Melius eſt ut pereat unus quam unitas, immedicabile vulnus enſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidendum eſt;</hi> and that they ſhould not forget this paſſage, nor miſconſtrue his Latin, <hi>pag.</hi> 39. He thus puts them in mind, and farther explains himſelf: Men (ſaith that Presbyterian) who lye under the guilt of much innocent Blood, are not meet Perſons to be at peace with, till all the guilt of Blood be expiated, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged, either by the Sword of the Law, or by the Law of the Sword. Thus they proved more barbarous than the Inhabitants
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:179945:7"/>of <hi>Meſech,</hi> and thoſe that dwelt in the Tents of <hi>Kedar:</hi> For when <hi>David</hi> deſired to be at peace with theſe his Enemies, they only made ready for Battel; but when our bleſſed King, whom they had deprived of his Power and Strength, did labour for peace, and ſpake to them thereof that were his Subjects, and ought in all Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to have obeyed him; they declared for his Murther, and if their young and unentred Lawyers will not condemn him to the Block, according to their King-killing Principles, they are ſure their well fluſhed Redcoats, who aſſaſſinated him in <hi>Effigie</hi> at <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter</hi> Cathedral, would murther him in Perſon when they had brought him back to the Houſe of Parliament; and for this exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable ſervice of theirs, they might without the Pope have received Abſolution from <hi>Stephen Marſhal,</hi> as well as for their Oaths. Thus the Presbyterians cry down the Pope and preach up the Jeſuit: Thoſe that cannot remember, yet if they can read muſt needs know, how <hi>Jack Presbyter</hi> run about with his Hue and Cry againſt Popery and evil Counſellors, and that his only deſign of raiſing an Army, was to extirpate the one (for whoſe entrance he hath made a wide gap) and to take his Majeſty from his pernicious (as they pretended) Council, and to make him an abſolute Prince: But they no ſooner got him into their Clutches, but according to their Traiterous diſtinction, they killed him in his politick Capacity, and only gave a terrible groan (I mean one of their ſighs) becauſe they did not murther <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> and that that curſed and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate blow was not celebrated by one of their extemporary Prayers: And though they may endeavour to make the World believe that they made prayers for the King, yet we never heard of any of their Petitions, until that Jackcall Cornet <hi>Joice</hi> had robbed them of their prey, and brought it to the Lion <hi>Cromwel,</hi> and when they ſaw him in his paws and ready to be devoured of him, they might ſay to God as the taunting and not underſtanding Jews did one to another, when our Saviour cryed out in his Agony, <hi>Eli, Eli, lama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſabacthani;</hi> they might ſay, let us ſee whether God will ſave him: For as to his Circumſtances, he was in the ſame capacity as our Saviour, and required as great a miracle to redeem him from the Block, as there muſt have been to have took our Saviour from the Croſs; for it was impoſſible for his Majeſty to have eſcaped, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs that God had impowered the Biſhop that was upon the Scaffold with him (like <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi>) by the throwing up of Aſhes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heaven, to have ſtruck them with Boyls, ſo that they might
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:179945:7"/>not have been able to have ſtood before him; or that he had enabled one of his Captains (like <hi>Gideon</hi>) with three hundred men to have diſcomfited this Hoſt of Midianites, or that his words (like our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours) ſhould have driven them backwards and made them to have fallen to the ground, when he told them he was their King; or that at his prayer God would have ſent him more than twelve Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions of Angels: No, <hi>Curſe ye Meroz, curſe ye bitterly the Inhabitants thereof,</hi> (thas is all good Subjects who will fight for, and will not fight againſt their King) <hi>Judg.</hi> 5.23. was the excellent Doctrine at <hi>Edghill, Newberry,</hi> and <hi>Naſeby</hi> Fights. Thus Presbyterians mock God, and never think of Death but talk of Heaven; and thus they blackned the whiteſt of Kings, and made the beſt of Subjects vaſſals: And now the Pope is on foot again, but whilſt they run him hard, they bark damnably againſt the King and his Council, and I believe would bite too if they durſt; intending to ſnatch up the Church of <hi>England</hi> in the Ring. They ſcorn to curſe (which according to the Original is diſrepect) the King in their thoughts, or that the bird of the Air ſhould tell the matter; No, theſe <hi>Rabſhekah</hi>'s call God, Men, and Angels to witneſs, and ſhew the thoughts of their hearts by telling of lyes, and talking ſcandalouſly of him in Coffee-houſes and the open Streets, never opening their Fanatical Chops but pretending they reveal as great ſecrets of him, as thoſe barbarous wretches did of his Father, who printed his Letters: Nothing now will ſerve their turns but conceſſions from his Majeſty, but if the King part with his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, then farewel property and hang up <hi>Magna Charta;</hi> for his Subjects ſhall no more be tryed <hi>per probos et legales homines,</hi> but run down by a pack of bloodhounds, who will prey upon our Eſtates as ſoon as <hi>John Catch</hi> doth cry dead, dead, hath paunch'd and ſtript their Bodies: Let us therefore that are right-bred Engliſhmen, who don't cut out our Religion by the Romiſh pattern or after the <hi>Geneva</hi> mode, nor our manners after the French faſhion; I ſay let us not be chous'd again by a humourſom and a rapacious faction, of our King, <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and all thoſe Priviledges that belong to all true Engliſhmen and good Subjects; and once more become Slaves and Vaſſals to this Tyrannous Kingdom of Saints, who cry out Religion and Liberty, but intend to clap on Shackles upon our Hands, Tongues, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences; ſo that if we don't ſubmit to what they pleaſe to call the Law and Reaſon of the Land, and to what their Saintſhips ſhall term Religion; the Dungeon or the Gallows ſhall be Umpire and decide the caſe. I am certain there is none of us too old, though many of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:179945:8"/>us may be too young, to remember how it was High Treaſon to paſs a Jeſt upon <hi>Oliver</hi>'s Noſe: How we were enſlaved by a Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, Arbitrary, and Oligarchical Government, who contrary to our known Laws oppreſſed us with illegal Taxes, and whilſt with much Travel we laboured for a Livelihood under them, how a parcel of Brewers, Draymen, and Coblers revell'd it upon the ſweat of our Brows. No, let them with their demure looks and canting tone cheat their zealous Siſters of their Bodkins and Thimbles, whilſt we that are good Chriſtians and Royal Subjects, follow the wiſeſt of Kings advice, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.21, 22. <hi>Fear God and the King, and meddle not with thoſe that are given to change: For their Calamity ſhall riſe ſuddenly, and who knoweth the Ruin of them both?</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:179945:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
